soft angie a radio episode 142 interview
with Kevin and Klaus from Opie this is
software engineering radio the podcast
for professional developers on the web
at se - radio dotnet as the radio brings
you relevant and detailed discussions
and interviews on software engineering
topics every two weeks thanks to our
audience and the partners listed on our
website for supporting the podcast
welcome this is so for those of you who
have been at the Tom DeMarco session
with Peter ooshka and at Linda's session
you might you know ask yourself can I
get rid of this guy asking the stupid
questions but this is yet another
session that we're going to do together
with the Essie radio podcast so that's
why I'm going to ask quite open-ended
questions about the topic and of course
this will be recorded and as I said in
the sessions before the original idea of
this was that audience which is you will
be able to ask questions so it would be
helpful if you actually did this so if
you have any question just let us know
and we'll also reserve time you know
towards the end for specific questions
and I'll come running to you and give
you my mic so you can say something
because you don't have another mic in
the room but that should work so I guess
we should get started and before we do
that before we get started with the
topic I think we should introduce the
the main act
I'm just the support act and I guess who
wants to start tell us and I guess I'm
listed first so alphabetically okay I
beat Klaus to it on two fronts
Kathleen Hanny I'm an independent
consultant and trainer based in the UK I
have a lot of interest in things like
software architecture programming
languages and development process and
yeah yeah
stuff like that okay I'm smart but I'm
working for a medical company building
lots of porting systems and I happen to
do a lot of architecture and release
management and stuff like that taking
care of processes as well and for
completeness my name is Marcus Firth and
I'm going to ask the questions so it's
about sustainable architecture so
sustainable software architecture
obviously so maybe you want to start
with doing the obvious thing which is to
define for software architecture and
then sustainable software architecture
what's a good shot okay the the idea
with this is a rather useful definition
of sustainable that we can actually take
from the United Nations report the
Brundtland report
sustainable development which implies
meeting the needs of the present without
compromising the ability of future
generations to meet their own needs so
very much from the point of view of
sustainability we are talking about
creating architectures software
architectures that have this quality
that we are able to affect what we need
now successfully appropriately without
messing it up for the future so as a
counterexample the first project that I
worked on the first commercial software
development that I did after University
yeah there was a there was a project or
the first company where the the changes
that were needed for the system took far
far longer than expected
far far longer than expected and the
system had have originally been written
by my boss it was one of these cases
where the boss writes a whole load of
code gets the business and then suddenly
you need more people to look after the
code and I met my boss saying you know
it didn't take us this long to do the
first version and you looked at it and
you say yeah I know I can see that's why
it's taking so long to do the second
version that is an example of not
sustainable so there is this notion of
balancing the present with the future
we're not that doesn't mean we are
designing for the future we are not over
parameterizing we're not second-guessing
the future but when we work with the
present we are not trying to burn the
bridges to the future so that is really
the notion of sustainability that
focusing on a bit about software
architecture here because software
architecture is not about foreseeing the
entire future that the system might see
sometime in some other universe and some
software architects think they need to
prepare for anything that may come up
and it's a virtue to build systems that
are configurable but it's also virtue to
just build systems that do what we need
today and this is also meant by
sustainable that we do what we need
today and not doing what we need
tomorrow as well
but not preventing what we might need
tomorrow it's a bit like the the
approach that the Aborigines in
Australia have so when they leave
someplace after a few days you will not
know that they have been there ok so
they they leave no footprint and talking
about software architecture yeah leaving
no footprint is not exactly software
architecture but having a minimal
footprint like if you if you talk about
all decisions in the project that you
make all technical decisions then
there's a lot of decisions to make and I
would call these architectural decisions
that are hard to change so we have that
notion there of there are many different
definitions of software architecture
some of them referred just to the
microstructure of a system the problem
is working out what is that
microstructure a more useful one and a
number of other people favor is the idea
of decisions that are difficult to
change and the definition from Grady
Booch emphasizes this idea of
significant decisions you know there was
where significance does it's defined by
cost of change so for a large class of
design decisions not all of them are
going to actually be critical in future
someone will be critical and more
critical than others and that can be on
a very detailed level like the locking
protocol for accessing a resource it's a
very detailed thing but it's still
important to get it right globally
exactly so therefore sometimes small
details
very large consequences so it's not just
about the big blocks there can be very
subtle details and that is partly the
the challenge we've seen various
problems in the past where people have
made would have been considered to be
implementation level decisions even in
things like wire level protocols I will
make that 16 bits we'll make that four
bits we'll make that 32 bits and what
happened is that that has become not a
minor implementation detail it's
actually become a fundamental constraint
on the way the system evolved it's not
the big box power point architecture but
nonetheless it is what we would consider
architecture in the sense of significant
decision so how do we make such
significant decisions a collection of
them creates a system how do we pursue
that notion of sustainability so its
sustainability related to a
maintainability evolvability platforming
dependability and abilities it saves on
words
it's a sustainable word because they
don't really use one word yeah you have
to use lots of words okay idea right
yeah there's a there's an essence of all
of these activities if you like the
continued all of the activities that
results in the continued development
deployment and lifetime of the system
what are all of those combined we are
interested in the ones that make them
sustainable which may be that
maintainability aspect on its own for
some systems but for other systems it
may be the evolved ability in other ways
if you talk about sustainable software
architecture and it's let's just phrase
that they Software Architect also needs
some sustainability because of all the
decisions that could become expensive in
the future software architects sometimes
have a current tendency to micromanage
all technical decisions which is a way
to be sure that every every engineer
really hates you and this is not a very
sustainable position so sustainable
software architecture I think can only
be done by software architects who
consider themselves sustainable this is
a really good pointer so so I think well
the reason why we have the session is
that sustainable of the architecture
probably isn't trivial so it's the
magnitude of the challenge somehow you
know
of the project size or the domain or how
can you you know classify the problem
depending on properties of the system I
don't think there's one easy answer to
that in terms of complexity we have a
number of different things that can
influence it in fact conveniently enough
we drop a mind map this was when I was
at classes home in Lubec last year we
sort of said what do we think about this
and we sort of came up with some ideas
in class and jotted down this mind map
loosely hierarchical but not but not
perfectly a various thoughts because
actually there's a whole space of
connected ideas in some cases what
you're looking at will be inherent
technical complexity of a system the
inherit technical complexity as in the
software solution itself is the thing
that is the challenge in other cases
it's the organization that surrounds it
so what defines something to be
sustainable or not is the way in which
the the company around it actually tries
to develop it so there's a lot of
different issues there there's impacts
of regulation there's impacts of the
scale of the software even simple
software ideas but lots of them sheer
the sheer mass of millions upon millions
of lines of code even if every
individual thing is somehow simple in
its own right
the overall mass is is somewhat
challenging so the sustainability the
degree to which you have to apply that
idea is definitely influenced by these
different aspects of scale clearly if
you have a two or three person project
and all the developers are co-located
and you're talking about a web style
release cycle that is at a very
different end of the scale to something
that is potentially life or business
critical distributed across multiple
sites across multiple time zones and has
a product cycle that reaches into
decades rather than weeks or months so I
don't there's necessarily a simple
answer it's more like a chart or a list
of factors
you can consider and sort of compare
against other classes of system well I
think team sizes is a key issue here we
were talking about making decisions
earlier and actually as an architect I
don't want to take every decision in the
entire system but what I really want is
local decisions by the developers while
they do their daily work on the other
hand I know that local decisions can be
really dangerous to the entire system to
the architecture then and within the
team we need a common sense a common
understanding of which decisions may be
hard to change in which not so in other
words when to refer to the architect and
when not and this is kind of a team
culture that must evolve and the larger
the team is and the faster it is built
up the higher the chances that you do
not get it right which relates to a
notion in that case that we can see in
terms of vision the vision of a system
is one aspect is there is the aspect of
the design vision the architecture in
that respect but one other aspect is the
shared vision that people have about how
the system should continue to be
developed and what is interesting is
that we normally talk about team size
and we normally talk about ohms like 9
or 10 as a sort of ideal maximum but we
also see very large software large-scale
software development is also considered
sustainable and there are a number of
open-source projects that have
demonstrated a very counterintuitive
model because of the yet team size is
ridiculously large it's it's not
co-located but what binds it together is
a shared vision and communication and
commitment and the commitment there is a
sense of personal commitment so there's
that notion that people share this idea
that we care about this in some way that
is a little bit deeper than a paycheck
if you are working in a company to get
that same kind of commitment requires a
slightly different approach but you
clearly people care about
they're their paycheck but you are
looking for something to be built up and
a level of understanding that probably
takes a little more nurturing a little
more encouragement and therefore will
take a certain amount of time and this
class said if you have this rapid growth
phase and then you split teams up for
reasons of so-called efficiency and you
scatter them across the globe is very
unlikely that you will end up with a
sustainable software architecture you
will end up with something but it is
unlikely to have these qualities about
sustainability there will be a lot of
adversarial us and then kind of notions
there yeah there's the idea of the
architect will if you distribute
architecture responsibility will end up
being polarized at each site architects
will declare war on each other with
their local tribes and over there their
local teams us against them but likewise
you you can get the other the other case
where you introduce a hierarchical
structure and chief architect is handing
down these things and architect turns
into architectures into cop and
micromanager so there's a the potential
for failure is very very large but it
does with this notion of careful growth
of team along with the careful growth of
software is the good is a good starting
point another was a sustainable start
rather than let's do it then we'll make
it sustainable so if I were a cynic I
would say we didn't talk about
architecture yet we talked about team
culture we talked about process we've
talked about how to communicate how you
know the the attitude of the people is
that intended I mean are you implying
that if you have you know a good
cultural team good process then good
sort of sustainable architecture will
result I think it's closely related I
mentioned the Aborigines and while an
attitude like I'm the big boss and I
know what I do and I'm the Hecker I
crank mines of code within an hour just
not appropriate they will not lay to
something that can be developed in the
team and that can be continued in
team so yeah it is related to to
attitude at least and maybe a bit about
process as well I'd say I mean I think
perhaps the first observation and this
is going to come as a big surprise to a
lot of people is that people involved in
software development you know what
they're human beings as well really you
most of them yeah yeah so the notion
there is that a lot of the standard
activities of human beings apply so yes
we have in that sense talked around the
notion of culture of groups of dynamics
of communication of process and let's
let's see how that relates the metaphor
of architecture that we import into
software development let's go back and
see what else architecture defines in
the world of the built environment
architecture defines a quality of what
it's like to live somewhere it tells you
about what it feels like to live
somewhere it tells you about the kind of
care that you might want to take it's
talking about the habitability of the
environment in which you live now all of
this applies directly to the notions
that we're interested in terms of
software just as just as we have they're
kind of the Churchill quote first we
make our buildings then our buildings
make us in that sense we are looking at
yeah it's a quote we have in there in
the book software architecture you know
remember that part you need to reread it
we build software like cathedrals first
we build them and then we pray so in
this sense what we're looking at is the
idea that the if you creating the right
vibe so I'm gonna guarantee a
sustainable software architecture but
what you want to do is create something
that is sympathetic to that that
encourages that kind of thinking the
attitude class just mentioned attitude
is very very important that the idea of
a kind of a yes we can approach to
software in the sense of it's very
topical if just let's just locate this
as being the week after the Obama
inauguration for those of you listening
in web time
so the the notion of the the I of the
attitude of yes software can genuinely
be soft yes in theory we should be able
to change it it is entirely reasonable
that we can do these things whereas in
many projects there is a sense where the
individuals are its do not feel that
that is possible they do not feel
there's a lack of communication with the
architecture class outlined earlier on
if you have everybody the only
unification on the team is that
everybody hates an architect that is not
going to lead to a sustainable
architecture if you have the idea that
yes this is possible you know we should
make this change yes we can make with
this change and we will make this change
because it feels appropriate at this
point in time if that's seen as a
possibility you have won half the battle
then we get into talking about the
technical aspect which is what
encourages these things which which
takes us into the actual the code space
how do we organize the code but very
much this idea of the code will reflect
something about the organization and
beliefs around it
it is very different you you can often
tell this when you look at an
organization's code you look at the code
and you can tell things about that what
the organization values and how they
push their projects forward the degree
of ritual the degree of chaos all of
these things are actually visible in the
code sometimes people are surprised at
this this isn't this isn't reading tea
leaves this is a case of archaeology how
do people live by judging the artifacts
about other they leave behind but in
this case we're looking at something
more anthropological the system is
hopefully still alive and so the
developers we are able to do something
about it it's not the Romans in this
case so yeah we then move on to the
technical aspects an important factor in
in the entire process and it goes into
into company culture as well so we've
just been to the keynote of Tom DeMarco
who really cares about corporate culture
and one aspect of sustainability comes
from within the the agile movement and
it is about option space option space is
like the possibilities that I still have
opened where I still can move to if I
want to and many organizations
developers and software cadets alike
feel like pressed to do decisions
because decision-making is a good thing
and clarifying things upfront is a good
thing and sustainable software
architecture is really about knowing
when to do which decision because there
are many decisions you need to do
upfront right but there are many many
decisions that you needn't do early on
and you are you are really better off if
you do not decide them this is quite
important we see these ideas per tick
articulated particularly in lean
software development and some of the
real options work that's going on and it
runs a gain counter to what many people
have as their attitude or belief as
class said people making yeah we value
your decisions doesn't matter whether
they're right or wrong but make a
decision whereas actually the things of
value is looking at the options don't
give me one option I often find this
when I'm talking to developers is that
okay so you give me one solution and
they're very proud now what about two or
three others we've already given you one
well no outline two or three other
alternatives but why would we want to do
that well let's just see what the space
looks like let's see what we could
explore it allows us to explore the
criticality of a decision well if we did
this this would be more open to change
but more complex to develop if we did
that that's open to change but not very
hard to develop so maybe we should
entertain that so the idea of being able
to always see the options the future
rather than as a single track we are
looking at the future as a sort of
forking road with lots of options
available to us and therefore we're
looking at balancing these options this
is very different to the idea that
people value a single item at a time and
this is very much a matter of attitude
and I have found that with a couple of
developers in the past where we've
outlined the the notion of alternative
designs and very much this comes from
work in patterns where explored
alternative variations and the
developers have been upset and annoyed
and they've been upset and annoyed
because I've given them more than one
choice they wanted everything to be
predetermined but this is not an
exclusive realm of
say novice developers I've had this with
architects as well they do not want
uncertainty they do not want this
exploration of design possibilities and
it's exactly this notion of design
possibilities and exploring that space
that gives us the sense of how to work
with this future that is uncertain and
untold okay we have a number of options
on the table what is the last
responsible moment that which we need to
commit to a decision because this is a
significant decision or what would we
need to know in order to make that
critical decision therefore that tells
us what we should be exploring either
technically or otherwise let's go back
to the customer and find out product
alternatives what other parts do they
have in mind that they haven't revealed
to us so we're looking at these various
different possibilities and it's very
much a very open space in this sense
which is very one's counter to linear
project cultures so we've talked quite a
bit about process culture and soft
issues so should maybe go on a little
bit to the more technical side so
clearly brackets now no not that bad no
I mean with properties of an
architecture do we need to track do we
need to make explicit how can we do
something about the assets we built to
make them more sustainable or is it all
of our process I guess not
no I mean there's a there's a cycle
between the two yeah the plays between
the two and the the aspect the the word
you just mention asset I think is very
important one yeah and so first of all
those society of evaluating your
software and looking at it from the
point of view of assets an asset is
something that has durable value and is
a value in itself in some way to your
business and be able to assess that
really want to look at the technical
properties of things what should we make
explicit what should be what should we
sort of make visible there are some very
simple properties let's start with one
of the the classics that people focus on
dependency management in terms of inter
component and have components so this
may be the first thing let me let me let
me clarify that go I'm going to use
component with
see I know what you mean it's not just a
big slab spaghetti monolithic what like
the system that I referred to earlier
that my boss had written yeah so there
is a very simple notion there that you
have some kind of that that your system
expresses some kind of partitioning
there is something in it
classes larger components components
with a big C this time layering in such
aspects you're looking at those you're
looking at those kind of partitions now
first of all can you see partitions if
you can't see partitions that's your
first warning sign this is bad you know
what you have is a slab of code it might
it might be a sort of obscure surrealist
form of poetry but it's not sustainable
the next thing is to look at the
partition you're partitioning just
simply separates two elements the next
thing is you care about the qualities of
that partitioning what are those
qualities and this is where we start
getting into things the good
old-fashioned classic properties of
cohesion and coupling and we start
looking at things like cyclic
dependencies does our system have an
apparent layering if it has or does it
have an aspiring layering an aspiring
layering is where people somebody an
architect draws up a layered diagram
often in PowerPoint but sometimes on a
whiteboard and it wants to be layered
because they've shown the layers but
when you look at the code what you see
is that it's not truly layered that you
have cyclic relationships between the
layering as such that system is
partitioned but it is not led they're
layering impervious suggests that there
is a strict direction to the dependency
and the direction is down carefully what
you are doing is you're describing
architecture with a big a with a capital
a because now you're talking about all
the virtues of software architecture and
nothing of this is particular
sustainable ah no I'm getting to that
because the notion there is why why do
these why do these properties one of
these properties actually matter this is
the one of the dirty little secrets so
back to your question about soft skills
and all the soft stuff actually yeah
it's all about the soft stuff it turns
out again another one of those big
surprises that your processor and your
processor doesn't actually
about how well partitioned your coders
your when when your code is run it
doesn't actually matter how well you
have named your classes your methods and
things like that it does not actually
matter the structure of your class is
the layering structure the cyclic
dependencies that you may have between
packages are not apparent at the
instruction level so the point there is
that the only reason we care about these
qualities and the only reason we have
these debates in software engineering is
because they matter to people the
copying cohesion are not for computers
covering cohesion or properties that
people are interested in you break
things out in a way that gives them a
single responsibility code does not care
about responsibilities people do it
makes it easier for me to understand why
do I care about good names for the same
reason I care about cohesion so the only
reason that we have these debates about
cohesion and coupling and this is an
important thing is there's nothing to do
with software there's no mathematical
purity here the reason we do it is
purely cognitive if we were creatures
with a very different model of cognition
we would end up with a completely
different model of software development
so yeah it's kind of all about the soft
stuff but expressed with curly brackets
so that's one of those technical
properties matter talking about
partitioning yeah that's right and I
would like to refer back to local
decisions that every developer needs to
make and if we if we look at system
properties like performance these are
really cute achill to them a lot of
systems so performance tuning is and
some systems in the forehead of every
developer and I know that local
decisions especially the forms related
local decisions can really make a hell
out of a system a mess that cannot be
maintained and thus it's not sustainable
because we cannot develop a second or
third version of it and so what I need
to do for the team be being the
architect in this in this endeavor is I
need to define a place where all
performance measures go so that nobody
feels buried that it's not being
addressed and people start addressing it
themselves at every opportunity they
find
and pectin can lead to that layering can
lead to that so if I define layers and a
half an abstraction layer for a database
or for some operating system for
persistence assistance really the best
example here and say okay we will do
performance tuning in there and not
elsewhere so if you have some object
that you need to query just go to the
persistence layer and query do it in an
orderly fashion and do not try to
optimize it that place we will optimize
within that layer once we find it
necessary but the team needs to trust in
the opportunity to do this performance
hearing later on so they have to
actually have a belief again this ties
back to the attitude they also need to
have another aspect there that ties into
this there's the belief in the
architecture but there's also a certain
understanding about again the change
ability sometimes people will counter
yeah yeah but sometimes you need to tune
performance outside of that layer the
approach that the attitude and the
technique at the level of the the
statement level of the code all the way
out to the larger level is very very
much the idea that you say well we will
do this until proven otherwise until we
reach a genuine contradiction that we
cannot solve at this level then we will
focus on work in that level so in other
words what we're saying here is we're
not saying that decision about where the
tuning of the data access will happen
we're not saying that decision is fixed
for all time what we've identified it's
not a static property but a stable
property something that is stable opens
the opportunity for future change but
what you're saying is yes it is possible
that we will encounter a scenario that
is critically bad or really tuning
cannot be solved at this level and then
we will reach that decision in other
words it's about the possibilities of
the decisions we will reach a point and
we will empirically demonstrate now is
the time to change something rather than
the second-guessing within each class so
in other words you want things to be
consistent and then if you decide you
need to change it you want to go from
one consistent state to another
consistent state in an orderly fashion
yeah
and it's understood by posit parties
explicit decision yeah host of stumbling
from one thing to another
yeah so there's that notion that you
don't suddenly discover that one
developer took it upon themselves to do
something and although it was a radical
act of heroism and you suddenly realize
actually that's undermined many of the
other architectural properties and
that's going to slow down the next
release or it's interfering with
somebody else's work particularly where
you're dealing with life cycles where
people have got multiple branches and
suddenly they try to merge them and you
end up with not just a kind of copy and
paste issue you've actually got you've
actually got a conflict of decisions
that have turned out to be architectural
there are significant decisions even
though they've been taken at the micro
level of the code you talked about
discovering you talked about performance
measurements to me it seems like the act
of measuring or discovering or checking
or monitoring some of those properties
we talked about it's kind of crucial
otherwise you don't know where you are
so how important is it to to check or
whatever you call this an architecture
to to to you know to know where you
stand how do you do this do you need to
do this yes so if you look at at the
real physical buildings that are
architected they also need to know where
they stand and whether something is
going wrong why they are built and those
buildings that have been adapted during
the growth are sometimes the most famous
ones so like the company lien Pisa
so yes it's necessary to measure where
you where you stand
the real issue is what actually do you
measure I'm asking its physical stuff
fairly simple to measure dependencies
among packages and components yeah so
this is this is the the no-brainer yeah
but that doesn't give you any you know
performance dynamic dependency behavior
dead log blah blah blah stuff one of I
think one of the the aspect is a first
of all there's no one fixed answer but
the danger here the danger here is that
so let's talk about what not to measure
or how you know when
not measuring the right thing one of the
is one of the problems is there's kind
of failure mode of pursuit of numbers so
in other words people start pursuing
every metric available yes just because
I can measure it doesn't mean that I
need to need to necessarily measure it
or need to retain it and at that point
they become overwhelmed and we know a
lot about these days it's easier to talk
about being overwhelmed than it was say
a decade and a half ago because we just
talked about things like spam spam oh
yeah so in other words you have as it
were data spam you know this is
informational spam becomes very
difficult to assess the situation
somebody's tracking so many numbers they
actually miss the real trends so we
could take a very different point of
view which is a problem focused one a
very simple idea of letters identify
things that are problems if you identify
something that is a problem
what is care what characterizes that
problem so let us just say that if we
have a development lifecycle that is
reasonably rhythmic it's it's it's got
lots of opportunities for feedback if
you have that kind of life cycle then
you immediately throw out the problems
whether through retrospectives very much
done by people or whether you're
actually looking at recurring
performance problems or the fact is you
know we always seem to spend our time
tuning things that in itself is
interesting okay well that's let's try
and see what characteristics the system
structure has that seem to correlate
with that so go out and find find the
things that seem to be causing you the
pain focus on those find the numbers
that seem to correlate in some way with
that and pursue those until they change
in an appropriate way this means that we
don't always end up with a fixed set of
metrics it doesn't mean that the metrics
that we are looking at the measures we
all get more broadly the observations
that we'll make are very much focused
are they're opportunistic we are trying
to solve a particular problem so rather
than walking in with a 50 individual
data points we are focused on maybe kind
of like or what I sometimes refer to the
metrics of the month this month we we
are going to focus on this area this
seems to be a recurring problem so we're
going to look at that but it's
identifying these recurrences and then
allowing you to focus what can we then
measure and so it's
it's very much again it's to do with the
cognition right sizing it for our mind
let's go and find things that seem to be
causing its problem
yes every time we change this so so a
very simple one would be to look at
correlation of changes so for each
requirement let us understand what the
scatter of changes so therefore when you
look at this you sort of say that's
interesting that requirement to
implement this requirement in say the
product backlog we have ended up with a
scattering of changes across the system
this rechange involved a large span of
change
so clearly the change was not located in
one particular I think we would like an
architecture that somehow a sort of
contains this change this is what the
purpose of partitioning is so that's a
warning sign in that sense if we have a
recurring theme of changes are scattered
over the whole system rather than
localized it obviously means that our
architecture is failing with respect to
localizing change so watching these
various trends becomes a very very
important aspect when we come to
measuring and what an architect needs to
measure it is definitely helpful to have
an early integration of the entire
system to have it running and to be able
to do like performance measurements but
talking about sustainable architecture I
I would like to ask whether we would
like to measure at all okay so what
would we like to measure so first thing
is about metrics they shape the mind of
all participants that that have a look
at these metrics so sometimes when I do
some metrics I never tell anybody
because I do not want to influence the
system so this is when I have no problem
yet the other thing is it's always most
interesting which in which components
change more frequently than others
because those are the the parts that I
consider unstable and so we can check
like how many versions have rejected but
rather than then doing this metric I
find it more helpful to to introduce
rules that allow change and that keep
the cost of change under control I'll
give you an example
we had a large team that was set
together from different teams and why
there were different teams
there were interfaces that had to be
stable because they were different teams
they had a contract and changing this
contract was so expensive that nobody
ever did when we managed to make this
one team and focus on integration
instead of deliveries we are also
managed to introduce a new change policy
that was whenever somebody changes
something he is also responsible to make
the system run again no matter what part
of the code he need to touch for that so
we omitted code ownership in this
respect and we found a stabilizing
mechanism like yes it was okay to change
and everybody had the decision in his
heads whether he wanted something to
change or not
he just had to make a drum and so
suddenly it became a great
responsibility to the engineers and say
okay this heard so so badly I really I
go through 30 classes now I changed this
or or not or even or not yes so I think
with that there is an element there it's
a really important point and one of the
reasons I favor this idea of the metrics
of the month first of all don't become
wed to the metrics but class also said
that sometimes choosing a metric can
change the way people respond and that's
exactly the reason you have this kind of
approach sometimes nominating something
pick something that people will respond
to don't pick things that they won't
respond to don't pick things that they
keep seeing every week and have done for
the last 12 months because they become
invisible maybe you have these items
that have been in your inbox for the
last year yeah they've become invisible
after a while and so the idea is that
sometimes you choose carefully something
that the only way you can change it you
respond to it the only way you can
change it is by improving some aspect so
there is this very careful very careful
game it's a very it's a very important
one people are influenced some that can
be used positively as well as negatively
but again there's also the deeper
reading and this is where we end up with
this notion that the danger that
problems of this kind of approach is to
be able to read a situation
appropriately so if I spot that a
particular component has a high defect
density so if I look at a particular
component it has a high defect density
we go through we go through the change
history and we understand it has a very
high defect density now there the normal
way that people will read that is it's
buggy the code itself is not well
written therefore we have a problem here
the deeper reading and the more
appropriate reading is to say what three
or four possibilities might lead to this
one is the code sucks that's why it's
buggy in other words it is genuinely bad
was not well written in itself another
reading is that this component is
heavily used by other components so we
find that in that case that actually the
other components have just as many
potential bugs but it's that they're not
exercised as much and I was the simple
reason we have found so many bugs is
this is so heavily dependent upon the
defect density is actually the same
elsewhere we have yet to discover it but
the third reading and the one that is
the most subtle and hardest to see but
is also often the case is that that
component is using another component
whose interfaces are difficult to use
and therefore they encourage bugs
because they create tedious and
error-prone interfaces we see this
history with buffer overruns and things
like that that use certain C libraries
it's not the code that's calling it that
is badly written although it has
problems it is the interface that has
caused the problems so therefore the
problem is not where you thought it was
the defect density is a pointer to the
real problem the problem is not where
the defects occurred it is either what
they were using in this other component
that we have no control over so it's
that recognition that when we are
looking at these numbers we need to do
something that is a little bit deeper
than just read the numbers and take the
first interpretation the sustainable
approach is to reimburse the component
partitioning and change that not just to
rewrite the code we have a question yeah
so concerning the sustainability trees I
mean when a wondering is can I even
answer it on on that level because yeah
they're sustainable the the architecture
is okay for a certain case
but it might be totally bad for a
different one and we obviously don't
know what's coming so the question is
can we should we think about something
else I mean should we think about the
sustainability on a different level than
the architecture itself should we care
about other things and obviously an sort
of analog on to that is the change
ability of code it's not related to the
code itself so much it depends on
whether you have good test coverage or
not because if you changed the code and
you're desperate you have obviously know
that something is wrong so the end and
you can be sure that it will be found by
the tests if you have good coverage and
therefore you will easily change the
code while otherwise with bad coverage
the code is not so changeable because
well nobody will tell you whether you
broke anything so I'm sort of wondering
whether even the title of the whole
discussion should be changed to
something else but I don't know what it
could be so you think there being a
contradiction because as far as I'm
concerned the code is part of the
architecture if you have no code you
have no architecture when you were
referring to the broader sustainability
I thought you were gonna talk about the
business case as far as I'm concerned if
you do not have sisters let's deal with
a potential contradiction can you have a
sustainable architecture with
unsustainable code yeah obviously not
that but that's not the point the
question is so I have a system there and
I look at the architecture through some
metrics as to just discuss and then I go
out there as a consultant and say well
this is obvious isn't sustainable I
think you can't do that because next day
the business guy comes through the door
and says well it hears in your
requirement and yeah I catch all of a
son should be changed completely so the
bottom line would probably be there is
no thing as a sustainable architecture
there is something else that we have to
think about to get sustainable systems
that we can still develop with without
exceeding costs and lots of money thrown
at the
at the project so and the question is
what might that be
I mean is that really on the etiquette
level that is the architecture it is the
set of decisions that the business can
invest in there from the business point
of view look at it from the business
point of view what is it that will
endure Marcus earlier on use the term
asset and that's quite a valuable one
there is more to this than just the
architectural side but I would say that
the sustainability aspect is still key
the set of decisions that you are making
in in terms of the development is still
critical you're right the business
decision could come along tomorrow that
is a black swan it's just out of nowhere
and it invalidates our assumption that
does not necessarily contradict what we
said we said this is open to change for
business as usual for a particular set
of trends I think we can identify
something that is a sustainable
architecture because we are looking at
everything we've said so far is very
much about looking at our changes over
time so it's very difficult on day one
to create a sustainable architecture it
is easier to years down the line to then
say yes we have created a sustainable
architecture can only judge in
retrospect exactly but there are there
are things that we can put into play
that improve the odds it's a game of
probabilities if you look a bit beyond
the the technical systems and this is
this is what you do when you do an
architectural review so you look at the
organization you look at the team and if
you then introduce sustainability I
would say you have reached a sustainable
organization if the organization
considers the team as one of the
deliverables of the project that is more
than just the architecture it's also the
team that lives the architecture it ties
back into where we started very much in
that sense as the the architecture we
talk about the people the process and we
also talked about this idea of
architecture defining a place where
these people actually work and live in
that sense so it kind of ease
architecture but it's a bit beyond the
classes hi my name is Martin and a
question and you talked a lot about
these adaptability changeable
tea over time and being as flexible as
possible is a good thing to do if you
didn't say being as flex we actually
contradicted that we said being as
flexible as possible is not a good thing
it's not a good thing no not as yourself
you don't you do not need anything about
the future so you need to be flexible
somehow I need you somehow I won't
change yeah so my question would be
isn't it if you think about the
architecture thing that it's very costly
to change wouldn't be the best the best
system a system without an architecture
that's an architecture it's not have no
architecture is an architecture well I
said let's go back what their definition
of architecture that we gave is the set
of significant design decisions if you
are able to come up with a major system
that has no significant design decisions
I think it's probably ain't a
significant system I thought that the
architecture is not the set of
significant design decisions but the set
of significant design decisions that are
costly to change significance is the
definition of your heart that's the
definition of significant okay yeah
significant it actually says the Grady
Booch quote is along the lines of
architecture is the set of significant
design decisions where significant is
the cost of change so if you can design
that's what we mean by significance is
the criticality the reversibility of
decisions this is where we're talking
about so if you can create as if you you
know it becomes an insignificant system
all systems have an architecture whether
you intended to or not the question is
is it a understood architecture or is it
a misunderstood architecture or is it
not understood at all is it an explicit
architecture in other words is it a
shared vision or is it just something
that is tacit and in the background of
people's minds these are the questions
we need to ask but there will be an
architecture ok well then then I think I
don't understand the the the difference
between design decisions and significant
design decisions because I have small
design decisions big design decisions
whatever
and if design decisions are changeable
over time and I think they need to be
changeable over time because we have to
adapt to changes in future and
basic thing I think that all design
decisions need to be changeable for the
future that's fine they could in
principle but let's actually just go to
a very simple thing let's just let's
just pretend okay let's just pretend
with Microsoft okay
oops this is going out on se radio well
there you go okay so let's just imagine
that there were Microsoft okay and we've
got Windows API and Windows API dates
back a number of years it uses a
particular naming convention Hungarian
naming convention which is you know as
general idea it's hard to learn and it's
also a slight insult to ten million
native Hungarian speakers but we're
going to come to the next question is a
name is an identifier in code is that a
is that architectural or not and I
always ask people this and everybody
says are you know naming variables is
not architectural Oh
I say okay so how easy is it would it be
from Microsoft to change the names in
their API how much would that cost has
anybody got any rough ideas if Microsoft
changed the naming conventions in their
IEP eyes how much would that actually
cost to change all of the dependent code
how are we talking billions or trillions
here so do you understand what I mean by
significant now as opposed to changing
the name of a local variable that's what
we're talking about is that all design
decisions in principle are reversible
because it is software it's not physical
in that sense but they have a different
degree of magnitude if it's local to the
team if its internal we can do something
about it
but I cannot just simply click on a
refactoring menu and say you know what
I'd like to extract interface from that
class over there that son wrote and then
suddenly all the code in the world go so
that's what we mean by significance
where how significant have we made the
design decisions that we need to be able
to flex and change so that's what we're
interested in I'm having sort of a bit
clearer that there is this difference of
degree but this is also a dependency
management really plays an important
role
because even with the within the classes
of our own system we can judge how
expensive change will be once we touch
the design of an interface I agree
completely good for me yeah yeah so we
all Microsoft please not for me that
would that would lead to not designing
systems out of big fundamentals big
architectures big application frameworks
or big windows API for example instead
of moving towards combining systems out
of very very small frameworks which I
can easily change so then maybe my
system becomes a set of very very very
small things that are easy to change
with very small designs instead of one
big design because it can change the
small design step by step or easily
without the recursive thing now when it
maybe I still have an architecture what
yes yes you have you what you just
described there was no no what you just
described there was an architecture you
told me how you were going to make the
decisions in your system you told me the
style of partitioning the properties
that you valued that is you have just
defined an architectural approach I had
a sense that you've does it well done
it's I like it and we does it cost
anything but what you've done is you've
actually that that idea of the shared
beliefs the culture architecture the
idea of architecture in some societies
is very much the way we build things
here that's how we do stuff that's the
vision that shared by the team what
you've articulated is a very clear
vision and it's not just clear it's a
nice vision we like it so therefore what
you've got there I mean it may not be
something we can use in all cases but it
is clearly an architectural vision and
you will be able to see when somebody
had contradicted it you'll be able to
look at the code a pleasure
so I'm somehow missing the odd unlike
child of documentation here you were
relating to the image of the forked Road
in the solution space
and I wonder why in this mind map or in
your discussion
nobody told anything about the look back
why we chose a decision for whatever
reasons at a given point in time so
where does the information come from if
I can change a decision or not okay so
where we got it we've got it somewhere
oh here we go if I look at this mind map
we have a nice little one there of
dependency management there's an
implicit explicit notion there there is
a couple of other nodes Evelyn so what
about documentation it's okay yeah we
haven't excluded documentation if you
like the notion that we haven't sent
extenders to documentation is not a
separate thing I hope it's not a
separate thing I don't want a little
branch off here that says and
documentation because what what exactly
what we have it's a bit let's put it
this way the way that documentation
normally gets treated is here all the
properties the system and documentation
that is the surest way of getting it
wrong yes I think you're suggesting I
perfectly agree there I'm leading is how
do you do the traceability how are you
technically implement that you record
and a document is a potential way of
doing that so okay so there's a we have
not said we're not going to isolate this
at just the just the level of
documentation so documentation can be a
written thing okay it can also be a
photographed thing or other use of other
images so there are other ways of
visualizing software structures so
sometimes what people will try to do in
fact I know somebody does a few years
ago what they looked at was
visualization of the trends in the
system and then you could annotate the
chair so in other words it's a
historical looking back and then
annotate this is why this was taken here
there and everywhere that's much richer
than what normally people mean by
documentation I
somebody made a suggestion at a
conference that I was at a couple of
years ago where they talked about trying
to track the significant decisions and
one of the ways we're doing this is
rather than writing it down what they
did is they they used a video camera
with a System Architect lock and they
had that they had a very simple idea it
was just a case of it that the
whiteboard talked that the architect
would normally give to other people was
was actually recorded instead of saying
well that's great now could you write it
down it's actually no that's actually
take the richness of that presentation
and they worked out it was actually
cheaper to do even if it took four takes
for a 60 minute recording that's still
done in half a day compared to the fact
that the architect we probably spend
weeks writing it so I I think I hit on a
very good point but I think
documentation is actually a very narrow
view of the recording space and that
sense I think it's very to capture the
broader history and that suggests want
to have the question answered if you
where do you get the information looking
back when did we make this decision and
can we revoke that or can't be ok here
is something we do in our projects we
maintain a wiki where we do all the
decisions that affect multiple projects
which is those decisions that we
consider important as of today because
the system is running it's out in the
market and and so on so we do some
maintenance and we do still do important
decisions there and actually when we
find ourselves raising some topic again
and again every other week we know well
this is a decision that we have made but
we were not ready to do yet so yet
another decisions a word just right and
we find the document in our wiki but we
do not track them so we attend we use
this week aid to document our decision
in some way that everybody who has at
least participated in those meetings
knows what we're talking about there is
some reasoning included but we do not
track back and my question would be why
would we need to check back
so we're coming closer to the end
something I was wondering about during
all the discussion here is is it
sustainable architecture or is it
sustainable architecting because we
about 70 or 80 percent of the stuff we
talked about was not about how the
software is structured what are good
architectural properties like I don't
know plugins or whatever it's really
about how do you organize the way of
finding the architecture of documenting
of tracing it of changing it and also
not just architecture but also the
implementation of the software to make
it sustainable right
and the keywords if the title of the
sessions are sustainable and software
it's not architecture so we could as
well have called it sustainable
development or just valuable Center and
just have the same discussion but
sustainable software more refers to the
product but right ok it's about the
process of creating the software ok but
there is another aspect that is that the
term architecture is not simply a
description this is one of those you
have to go and look at a dictionary kind
of things is that the term architecture
is not simply a description of the
software asbill architecture also
defines the name of the discipline I
think it's very important and indeed
some people actually object to the word
the use of architect as a verb
architecting although I know perfectly
respectable books that have had that in
their title but there's a notion that
architecture is is embracing these
things so it's the the discipline view
as well as the actual structure view and
yeah you're right there is a very
important point to distinguish that
those are the things that are going on
ok I know it's risky to ask you to come
up with a closing work because I'm going
to ask close for the reason that it's
going to be short or so so ok so what is
it that you want to leave our audience
littles with now that we come to the
close of the thing I would like to
encourage the audience because
everything that we did sounds scary
we said well you need to leave the up
space large you need to know when
decisions to take when you need to know
what effects that code is in
and will later disaster or not and
everything about this culture it's
really scary so how do you know what to
do right and it says yeah
first thing is it takes experience yeah
the second thing is this is one of my
Mikey met metaphors for the way I like
to architect that is I do not I do not
buy into into buildings this is not the
the correct and under analogy I like the
the medical metaphor so I'm kind of I'm
kind of a doctor then when the system is
up and running and the team is up and
running we still do important decisions
but we do them when something is found
to be ill yeah and this is when to step
in and you will know so that's also why
you wrote those patterns that diagnose
this metaphor right about that you need
you need a lot of experience that if you
talk really about medicine there there
are thousands of years of documented
experience that we do not have readily
available yet so if I'm any attitude if
you manage to cope with the below one
minute then you I think don't wait a
special award yeah yeah okay what Klaus
said okay
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio software engineering
radio is an educational program brought
to you by hillside Europe if you want
more information about the podcast and
all the other episodes visit our website
at SE - radio dotnet if you want to
support us you can donate to the SU
radio team by our website or you can
advertise for se radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
links and the select button to contact
the team please send email to team at se
- radio net or if it is specific to an
episode please use the comments facility
on the website so other people can react
to your comments this episode of se
radio as well as all other episodes are
licensed under the creative commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks to Charlie
Crowell and the pot size Music Network
for the music used in this show the song
is called Vegas hard rock shuffle